<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The work of sin (in the flesh) condemned and the power of the enemy (in and over the creature mankind) by spiritual weapons resisted, and warred against ... / R.B.</title>
            <author>R. B.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1663</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 55 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 13 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-12">2011-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A27306</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing B175</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R11933</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">11690714</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 11690714</idno>
            <idno type="VID">48198</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A27306)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 48198)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 806:21)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The work of sin (in the flesh) condemned and the power of the enemy (in and over the creature mankind) by spiritual weapons resisted, and warred against ... / R.B.</title>
                  <author>R. B.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[2], 22 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>[s.n.],</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1663.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in Huntington Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Society of Friends --  Doctrines.</term>
               <term>Sin --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2011-01</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-01</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-03</date>
            <label>Ali Jakobson</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-03</date>
            <label>Ali Jakobson</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:48198:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:48198:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>THE WORK OF SIN (in the Fleſh) Condemned, and the Power of the Enemy (in and over the Creature mankind) by Spiritu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>al Weapons reſiſted, and Warred againſt; In a Controle of the dark Reaſon and Imaginations and Conceivings, of Fallen Man in and under the curſe of the Law that was added becauſe of tranſgreſſion;) AND Wherein is opened and unfolded, by and from the ſpirit, of Truth, the Miſtery of much and many Truths con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tained in the holy Scriptures, in theſe Several particulars of the Doctrine of holy Faith.</p>
            <list>
               <item>1. <hi>Concerning New Wine put into old botles, or a new peice of cloath into an old Garmen<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> &amp;c.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>2. <hi>Concerning the Wedding garment which many in this day are found without &amp;c.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>3. <hi>Concerning the fruitleſs Tree that cumbers the ground.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>4. <hi>Concerning the words of Chriſt, fear not him that can kill the bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy &amp;c. In which hell death and judgement are treated on, and ſuch likewiſe diſcribed who are already in it;</hi> And</item>
               <item>5. <hi>Whereby the difference of the Creatures ſining againſt the Judgement of <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>od (in a time of ignorance) and againſt his mercy (in a time of knowledge) is diſcourſed</hi>
               </item>
            </list>
            <p>Which is a precious warning and viſitation of repentance, to all the world, but eſpecialy to thee! (O <hi>England.</hi>)</p>
            <p>By one <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>hat hath remained hidden (in the retiredneſs of ſpirit in and with. God a friend to all <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ouls and love<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> of <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ruth and righteouſneſs R. B</p>
            <p>
               <hi>London</hi> Printed in the Year 1663.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb facs="tcp:48198:2"/>
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:48198:2" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <head>Concerning New Wine put into old botles, or a new peice of cloath into an old garment &amp;c. Wherein is diſcribed the difference between a man changed <hi>[in heart and nature]</hi> by the truth of Judgement <hi>[in God,]</hi> and men changing their Judgements and opinions <hi>from one perſwaſion to another &amp;c.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>IN the begining of creation, the creature was created change<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able, that is in a condition that might be changed <hi>(or ſubject to vanity and change)</hi> not willingly, but by reaſon of him that ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jected the ſame in hope: this condition was not wholly ſubjected to the power of the enemy <hi>[without, but in the creature,]</hi> though as a creature, he was ſubject to temptation and to be tempted by the power of the Enemy <hi>(in the creaturely ſtate of nature [in and of his body,] and both body and ſpirits compoſure;)</hi> for yeilding or ſubjection was the creatures frame <hi>(in which he had properties and qualities and faculties acting him,)</hi> and in that was he a ſubject to what did or ſhould raign over him <hi>(which was or ſhould be his Lord;)</hi> for the enemy could not have entered the creation of God; out by and in him <hi>(whoſe place was without [the creature and creation of God,] where he ſecretly and hiddenly wrought (in the miſtery of darkneſs and nothingneſs and emptineſs) which made for the exalting the name and Justice of <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>od (in what he was reſolved to glory) over the enemy and ſpirit of enmity (that wrought its own torment in the dark unconceivable wombe and miſtery of eternities ſufferance:)</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Thus was the creature in the cauſe of his change, <hi>from and in the condition he was firſt-placed and ſtated in,</hi> and had and hath theſe conditions they bear <hi>(in the fall from and tranſgreſſion againſt God, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>herein the work and power of changeablety is manifest;)</hi> And <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>udgement was and is a condition <hi>[in the creature]</hi> whoſe p<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>oper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>y, faculty, and quality is alter<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ble <hi>[to and in him]</hi> as to a ſtate or <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>ates he doth, or may poſſeſs; And it is become an eaſy thing <hi>o the creature,</hi> to change his Judgement from one thing to an <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="2" facs="tcp:48198:3" rendition="simple:additions"/>
or from opinions and perſwaſions <hi>[in the world]</hi> as the world doth alter and change; but this is but to put new wine into old botles, or a new peice of cloth into an old garment; for the proper work of trueth <hi>[in God]</hi> or God <hi>who is a ſpirit of trueth,</hi> is to change the heart of the man, <hi>whoſe nature is old, and hath the old wayes and courſe of the enemyes road to walk in,</hi> and ſo creat all things new; then is the prayer and deſire of the righteous and upright wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſed and fulfilled <hi>(creat in me a clean heart O Lord! and renew a right ſpirit within me;)</hi> and the heavens and earth are new created, and every and all deſires of the ſoul are new and after new things <hi>(even in the Lord and of his Kingdom;)</hi> and thus may creatures and people ſee whether the work of the Judgement of God hath place <hi>in their hearts,</hi> and whether Judgement be ſo ſet up <hi>in the earth,</hi> that the inhabitants may learn righteouſneſs; for it is Gods work to Judge <hi>the earth</hi> in righteouſneſs, and they in whoſe heart the ſpirit of Judgement and burning doth work <hi>(to the changing it, and them in it)</hi> are ſuch in whom God is come to dwel, and where he ſitteth as a refiners fire, and fullers ſope, <hi>to purefy the droſs from the ſilver &amp;c.</hi> in that the heart is the true ſeat of <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>udge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, and the place where the ſpirit of truth <hi>[in all creatures]</hi> doth Judge for God, and work its work <hi>firſt,</hi> before any thing can be retained <hi>that will hold;</hi> for where trueth or trueths are not held and retained in righteouſneſs <hi>(in the righteous part and heart,)</hi> its Judgement is againſt the man <hi>(that thus treaſures up or retains [in the wrong part] what works and makes againſt him;)</hi> and the man cannot hold and retain it <hi>[to his lives end]</hi> in any comfort or rejoycing <hi>[therein]</hi> that may appear, and ſeem to be his ſtrength <hi>[in Judgement,]</hi> but it breaks him, even the veſſel or creature <hi>(that ſtrengthneth Judgement againſt ſelf [himſelf] by his thus hold<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing and retaining it in that part it is againſt him in;)</hi> for it is a very dangerous thing for the creature to hold or retain Judgement in that which makes againſt him <hi>(though it be the Judgement of the ſpirit of trueth)</hi> in that in this day is the wrath of God revealed from heaven againſt all them <hi>that hold the trueth in unrighteouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs,</hi> and ſuch are children of wrath, filled with the wrath and indignation of the almighty God <hi>(which we were [by a nature we
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:48198:3" rendition="simple:additions"/>
were born and brought forth in] as well as others;)</hi> yea thoſe hate the Judgement of God (that thus retain it in the wrong mind and nature <hi>[the nature of hatred,]</hi> that is the hateful nature of enmity againſt God and his good ſpirit of trueth, <hi>which God hates,</hi> (in referance to the enmety therein and thereof <hi>is retained</hi> againſt the work and workings, and operation of ſuch his good ſpirit,) <hi>where the truth is not received in the love thereof;</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And this day is God come forth to work a mighty change in the creature and creation <hi>(the earth and world, which is the work<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manſhip of his hands)</hi> for behold he is creating all things new, and <hi>Ephraime</hi> is come up before his remembrance, that hath ſought to reſt and ſettle her ſelf on the old leeſ and draggs of the <hi>worlds defilements,</hi> and liberty and eaſe of the fleſh, and all fleſhly mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions and deſires: and God hath been emptying her from veſſel to veſſel, untill ſhe is well nigh refined wine <hi>from the leeſe</hi> and the ſavour of the old nature and veſſel is well nigh loſt, and the ſet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tlement left, <hi>in the burning and inflaming body of nature [to Gods praiſe and glory] his Judgement hath waſted and conſumed the evil in and of:</hi> Oh that there was a heart for theſe things to enter! and that men would receive and lay up wiſe ſayings! for where trueth is received <hi>in the love thereof,</hi> the Judgement of trueth is <hi>ſeen</hi> not to be againſt, but for the creature <hi>of God;</hi> and he that is in and hath the love of the Judgement of the ſpirit of trueth <hi>po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeſſing his heart and ſoul,</hi> hath the love and charity of God <hi>there,</hi> to inform the Judgement, <hi>of the work and works of the enemy</hi> (the ſpirit of trueth in Judgement <hi>[in God]</hi> firſt made and is ſtill bent againſt, for the creatures preſervation out of hurt <hi>under the power of the enemy;)</hi> and ſo, Judgement is kept on the work of the e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nemy <hi>(that would deſtroy the creature or creation of God, the work<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manſhip of his hands, in which a ſence of the love of God ſhould re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>main)</hi> in this day Gods ſalvation and love is ſprung up to the crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture and creation, which groans and waytes to be delivered, and travils together in pain, <hi>for the adoption to wit the redemption of the body,</hi> that the perſons and ſpirit of creatures might be ſaved alive, and as the love of God is <hi>hereby</hi> come into and dwelt in, where our brother <hi>that we ſee</hi> is loved, ere God can be ſeen and loved and o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>beyed <hi>(in the heart;)</hi> what remains but a ground for manefeſting the ſame?</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="4" facs="tcp:48198:4" rendition="simple:additions"/>And hereby, what would lead into the work of deſtruction the hurt and enmity <hi>of the creatures life,</hi> is kept out of, and not joyned to <hi>[in the perticular or general]</hi> and this is the way he is leading his creature <hi>in and by,</hi> where the work of the enemy is wearied and tired out, and the creature made weary of the weight and burden of ſin, and willing to ſet down and reſt from his own labour <hi>with God</hi> and ſo hath reſt and peace <hi>with <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>od</hi> in the ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies deſtruction, he is not joyned and united to <hi>(in heart or ſpirit)</hi> neither hath any love towards; but hates the work and workings of the enemy and enmity <hi>[to the creatures life and well being]</hi> with a perfect hatred (for the ſake of God and his creature, in whom the love of his trueth <hi>to raign</hi> ought to be reſpected, for the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fort and rejoycing of whatever God is pleaſed to work and act <hi>in the earth and heart of ſuch creatures;</hi>) for that which leads into the power of deſtruction, and under its ſpirits guidance, doth <hi>firſt</hi> lead and guide into deſtraction, whereby that ſeeming zeal <hi>for God or the Lord,</hi> is for a power of dominion that is God <hi>in and of the world of ungodly (that vallues not the creatures good and pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſervation in an equal concern with the honor and glory of that God they have a zeal for, and love to the way of;)</hi>
            </p>
            <p>So who is in the love of the trueth <hi>revealed in the heart,</hi> and that they know and are acquainted <hi>with,</hi> and the Judgement thereof reſpects <hi>in their own particulars,</hi> loves that which ſhews the evil of all biterneſs of ſpirit and emnity <hi>againſt the work and will of God (in which is an equall concern of his creatures good, in that will and work;)</hi> but the biterneſs of ſpirit it loves not, neither the enmity to the ſpirit of God, which he learns <hi>(by the evil of what he therein ſees in it)</hi> to come out of, as that which is no friend to God nor his creature; therefore ſhould he be a friend to it, he ſees he ſhould befriend the enemy of God and his own ſoul, and ſtrengthen the enmity and hatred of God againſt ſelf <hi>himſelf,</hi> in countenancing or loving what God hates, and ſo make the Judgement of God in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tolerable and hard to be born, <hi>as ſuch work of the enemy is pitied at home,</hi> which by loving that which diſcovers the evil and danger hereof, he is thereby preſerved from, &amp; ſuch evil &amp; danger prevent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed;
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:48198:4" rendition="simple:additions"/>
and ſo nothing is broken and diſtracted <hi>o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> the work of God (in th Judgement and underſtanding of the creature)</hi> neither ſo comes forth <hi>in the world,</hi> through a haſtineſs of ſpirit <hi>in ſuch the creature</hi> (in referance to ſelf and the ſelfiſh favour <hi>of the minds paſſion,</hi> in the predomenacy of any overflowing humour;) but the heart is made new, from whence inordinacy of paſſion <hi>(in ſuch favours)</hi> do ariſe, and where the humors have had predomenaci, and the cauſe hereof <hi>(which is the creatures deſtruction in the particular or generall)</hi> dyes from him, and he from it: and ſo is in and of a healing, ſaving, ſound ſpirit, ſound and wholeſome <hi>in and under Judgement,</hi> being ſeperated from the old, and the old nature and ſpirit <hi>of the world,</hi> that had the old affections, which are crucified to him, as he is to the world <hi>(in which the inordinaci of love and aff<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ction wrought in and after earthly things;)</hi> which ſhould the work of the enemy be countenanced <hi>in the creature</hi> and a pity in the heart lurke and remain to <hi>it, that may foster the evil,</hi> then is Judge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment ſtrengthened againſt the creature <hi>(in that work of countenan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cing the enemies power)</hi> and ſo becomes intollerable <hi>to the creature,</hi> and can not be born, but leads into diſtraction and into a broken torn condition: but the treaſure being in heaven <hi>(where all things are new made and created)</hi> the ba<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> is without holes; for the heart is alſo there, and the affections ſet on things above; And this is that heart and minde that what hath been (empted from veſſel to veſſel) is now retained in, and though it hath been the cauſe of braking. <hi>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>in many veſſels,</hi> a heart is now felt and found that can retain the ſavour <hi>of its work</hi> to its lifes end; and rejoyce in and ſpeake well of the ſame; that like the good houſholder, can bring out of its treaſury things new and old; for the heart being made new; there is dayly new and freſh experience of Gods good<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs; and though old things are done away, yet the remembrance of Gods goodneſs and glory <hi>(who is the worker)</hi> brings up all be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the creature, to exalt the goodneſs of God, and to put the creature in a dayly remembrance of what he is, <hi>as in and to himſelf:</hi> And here is no more ſea, nor confuſed heaps of unſtable waters, and raging waves, that foame up and out their own ſhame; nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther is the broken and torn brought before God, and offered to
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:48198:5" rendition="simple:additions"/>
him <hi>as a ſacra<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ice;</hi> Yea And here is neither old wine in new bot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tles, nor new wine in old botles, <hi>whereby the botles ſhould break, and the wine be ſpilt on the ground,</hi> but new wine is put in new botles, and both are preſerved, and the garment is all new, and ſo no rent <hi>(which new cloath to the old garment might make the rent worſe;)</hi> but a liquor is in the veſſel, that hath been powered and emptied <hi>from veſſel to veſſel</hi> untill all the evil ſavour of what was found and remaines <hi>(in the firſt veſſel,)</hi> be l<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ſt and conſum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed; and it is, <hi>though the veſſels be altered,</hi> and that is remaining, <hi>which can bear and retain the laſt ſavour and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>aſt of Judgement<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
               </hi> oh bleſſed, bleſſed to God for ever! for thi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> is the win<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> that chea<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>eth the heart of God and man, it makes it glad, as we come to drink it a new <hi>with Chriſt</hi> in the Kingdom of heaven.</p>
            <div type="part">
               <head>
                  <hi>Concerning the wedding Garment,</hi> which many in this day are found without &amp;c.</head>
               <p>This is the day that <hi>the light</hi> of God is ariſen, and his glory doth ſhine and break forth in the earth and world <hi>in great luſter<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </hi> through the heart and ſpirit of his creature, and he that dwells in the light that no mortal eye can approach unto <hi>(in this day Imor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tality and life is come to light through the Goſpel)</hi> is come down among men to tabernacle, and the ſpouſe of the great and mighty prince hath made her ſelf redy, the chaſte wiſe virgin <hi>(tho bride the lambs wife)</hi> that hath joyned with the ſpirit <hi>of God,</hi> and to it is found united <hi>in deſire,</hi> that as the ſpirit ſaith <hi>come,</hi> ſo the bride <hi>(with the ſame voice)</hi> ſaith come; And ſhe hath the <hi>wedding</hi> gar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment on, the fine lining <hi>(white and clean)</hi> which is the righteouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs of the Saints, <hi>the covering of the ſpirit of God;</hi> And all that are without this covering <hi>(in this day)</hi> are found naked, and men come to ſee their ſhame; And though they are of them that may be come into the bride chamber, yet being found, not having on the weding garment, <hi>even it that covereth and hideth all the creaturely deformity and weakneſs and infirmitys,</hi> they are never<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>theleſs ſhut out <hi>(into utter darkneſs)</hi> where is weeping and wail<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, and gnaſhing of teeth.</p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="7" facs="tcp:48198:5" rendition="simple:additions"/>A feaſt is prepared <hi>in this the great day of God,</hi> and proclamation thereof is gone forth <hi>into the earth and world,</hi> yea very many hath been invited thereto; for the table God of hath been ſpread <hi>in the wilderneſs,</hi> and thither hath many been alured, to a feaſt of fat things, of marrow, and wine from the Lees well refined, and multitudes yea very many hath fallen in this conditi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on <hi>[by the way]</hi> through unbeleife and unfaithfulneſs of heart that have been found murmuring and repining againſt God, <hi>as a hard maſter, or hard dealer with them,</hi> who hath thereby took occaſion to beat their fellow ſervants <hi>(themſelves being in the occaſion of the hardneſs and of bringing thither;)</hi> but that way are they to return which they went forth, even through ſufferance to the man <hi>that hath grew up in and under the ſufferance of his ſpirit;</hi> and the winter muſt be indured and the wilderneſs paſſed through, which will try every mans works <hi>[of what heart they are]</hi> for the firſt appearance of the bridegroom hath been at midnight, and the fooliſh Virgins <hi>as well as the wiſe</hi> hath come forth to meet him, and hath had Lamps trimed, but no oyl was therein, yea the un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prepared hath had a lamp, <hi>and it was trimed,</hi> they have come into the feaſt <hi>(very many that were invited,)</hi> but without a Wedding garment on, and yet room hath been <hi>at the feaſt,</hi> for ſuch that are compelled to come in, and all that are not arrayed <hi>to the content of the maſter of the feaſt</hi> are nevertheleſs put by ſhut out, and cannot hold the tryal <hi>of what is to come,</hi> but will come ſhort of the reſt prepared <hi>for the people of God,</hi> in the flying from the one <hi>(to wit the winter)</hi> they are found ſhort of the benefit of both <hi>(even that which indureth the winter, and comes to ſet down in and injoy and poſſeſs the ſabba<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>h and reſt of God)</hi>
               </p>
               <p>And all them that are not come to taſte of the goodneſs of God, that yet do not taſte and ſee how good he Lord is, are ſhort of ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perience of the good of theſe things; they taſte not of the dain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties of Gods houſe, and are not arrayed with that which makes lovely <hi>in Gods eye,</hi> and where a condition is pleaſant and refreſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able; but in that eternal eye are compreh<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>nded, in the ſtate of en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mity <hi>(notwithſtanding their profeſſion;)</hi> for though a call and Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clamantion is gone forth into the earth and world, <hi>unto the ſins of men,</hi> and as many have been invited, ſo very many hath been come<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pelled
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:48198:6" rendition="simple:additions"/>
to come in <hi>(in this day and hour)</hi> to fill up the room in the houſe of God <hi>[that was once empty <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>o gu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </hi> yet here <hi>alſo,</hi> even at the door or out of the houſe, they have <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> a repulſe <hi>(in an un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prepared condition)</hi> much more in a condition altogether a ſtranger to theſe thing, and the life of his covenant of promiſe how there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore doth the word of the Lord run thorugh me! prepare, pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pare <hi>to meet the Lord by repentance;</hi> that after the armor of God hath been put on, and thou come to the certain ſound <hi>of the trum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pet,</hi> and art prepared for the batle the whole armor of light, the ſhield, of faith, the breſt plate of Salvation, and helmet of righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſneſs, having on thy head the crown of the victory of truth, with the loyns of thy mind girt up to God, and thou made ſtrong in him <hi>in mind and ſoul,</hi> thou hereby may be diſtinguiſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed a Warrier in the army of the mighty God, and under his banner come <hi>(which hath been diſplayed in the ſight of nations;)</hi> And having done all, thou may be found <hi>in patience,</hi> having the garment of a meek and quiet ſpirit, <hi>which with the Lord is of great price;</hi> here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in God will receive thee <hi>as a tryed ſtone,</hi> he will meet thee <hi>here</hi> as a dove in the wilderneſs <hi>that wants her mate,</hi> as a widdow in the deſart <hi>that hath diſpleaſed the favour of her huſband;</hi> as a prodigal ſon, and the garment is put on, the wedding garment, the gar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of praiſe (in which thou mayeſt again be joyned, to God <hi>(in a new and freſh covenant;)</hi> oh this is the ſume of all! the ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance of all! that having done all we may ſtand, <hi>ſtand to our own maſter,</hi> not think ſo, but be warned by that which learns to take heed <hi>leaſt we fall.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>To be covered with righteouſneſs <hi>is the thing,</hi> to have that over all a mans garment, his cloathing, a wedding garment <hi>and it put on;</hi> then what can harm? or who can make afraid? To feel truth within <hi>(in the heart,)</hi> to God, to refreſh the ſoul, and to men to have the like mind <hi>of truth and righteouſneſs,</hi> it is hereby worn <hi>in the worlds ſight,</hi> then is the man covered and cloathed with it, as that in the heart is brought forth into action and manifeſtation <hi>(when the time comes that the excerciſe thereof is called for in the world;)</hi> for it is both food and rayment; oyl to the wounded, and food &amp; rayment to the hungry and naked, and refreſhment to the
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:48198:6" rendition="simple:additions"/>
weary ſoul; And the more is profeſſed, the more is required and called for <hi>(in anſwer to ſuch profeſſion)</hi> and then if there be a ſtay behinde <hi>the call, the voice,</hi> he is compelled to come in <hi>[very like]</hi> to ſee and behold the dainties of Gods houſe; but he hath not power to touch thereof, much leſs to taſte, but that is his tor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, <hi>to ſee that which he hath no appetite to, that is not reliſhable to his taſte</hi> And <hi>if ſo</hi> that is not prepared for him nor he for it: But of this are all the upright in heart perſwaded, and that they have right to the tree of life, to the paradice of God, to the riches and dainties of his houſe, notwithſtanding all their failings and back<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſliding <hi>which God hath healed freely for his own name ſake,</hi> having him that all the treaſures of knowledge and wiſdom are hide in, <hi>on their ſide,</hi> whom God freely gave for us all, and with him ſhall he not freely give us all things; They have reliſh, they have taſte and ſavour, cloathed they are <hi>(on the right hand and left)</hi> and do feel truth to be the garment and covering <hi>they are cloathed with,</hi> and it warmes them without, and refreſheth them within <hi>(to feel themſelves in the life of truth profeſſed)</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>
                  <hi>Concerning the fruitleſs Tree</hi> that cumbers the ground &amp;c.</head>
               <p>The ground of this worlds eſſence and being <hi>(the heart thereof, that was an honeſt and upright heart in Gods creation)</hi> was once good and the root of the tree <hi>alſo</hi> that God once planted a truly right noble ſeed, and the body and branches, that grew up from the good ground and root <hi>(as it ſtood good and in innocency)</hi> in like manner was good, and brought forth the fruit of his praiſe and honor, and as one man did <hi>Adam in innocency and uprightneſs</hi> in joy and poſſeſs the benefit of this good <hi>(before nature degenerated into the plant of a ſtrange vine (then were ſower grapes brought forth unto the Lord, bitter and unpleaſant to taſte; the grape of Sodom and apples of Gomorah; And the ſervants of the Lord were beaten and cruelly uſed (that were ſent for the Lords own;) for he looked for grapes, and behold vvild grapes,)</hi> and he had no benefit of his vine-yard: wherefore he began to brake off the branches, and to gather in others, that might bring forth better fruit, and from
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:48198:7" rendition="simple:additions"/>
the Eaſt and Weſt, and North and South, to call in and invite to come and ſit down <hi>in the kingdome,</hi> with <hi>Abraham Iſaac,</hi> and <hi>Jacob,</hi> where <hi>chi dren of the kingdome are ſhut out,</hi> yet were not the branches <hi>that were gathered in,</hi> to boaſt themſelves againſt them that were broken of, and caſt out, but to remember and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſider the root bares them, and not them it.</p>
               <p>And theſe th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ngs were ſeen and done in a green tree, ere the body was thorough grown, or any thing quite ripe and dry ready for the fire <hi>(of unquenchable burnings,)</hi> and before the fruit <hi>of ſuch works and actions</hi> could manifeſt the hidden works of darkneſs, and fruitleſsneſs of what is brought forth <hi>from the mistery of Ini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quity,</hi> againſt which the fury of Gods ſoul is bent; And had he not longed for figgs, to taſte of the fruit of what his own right hand had planted, never had the curſe been felt, And it was not ſo much the degenerate plant, the unpleaſant taſted tree and fruit, that the curſe was to, or that drinks the dreggs of the fury of God, and his wrath and indignation to the wicked; ſo is its ſin ſtreng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thened (againſt the favour, love, and mercy of God, that not onely lets ſee this ſtate, but a way to eſcape a further and greater danger is made known <hi>in and by the ſame diſcovery</hi>) in reference to what is come forth againſt the dry tree; for the fruit is already ripe and well nigh gathered in, and the harveſt of Gods favour <hi>(i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> the general,)</hi> near over <hi>(as to and in many particulars, the work hereof hath been manifeſted and witneſſed in;)</hi> therefore hath this tree over ſtood its time, <hi>(that which hath no fruit to God in time of vintage,)</hi> and offends more then Gods Judgement; for his fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vour and grace is hereby ſo abuſed and ſinned againſt, that its well nigh wearied out <hi>(as his Judgement had been offended wh<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap> ſower grapes were brought forth;)</hi> this God bore for thy ſake, <hi>hi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> creature,</hi> and for thy weakneſs ſake and want of knowledge <hi>(of his mind and will, and the counſelings of his pure ſpirits work and workings;)</hi> becauſe his ſervants were not altogether ſent away empty, but brought unto him ſuch as the ground bore; but where the ſervants of the Lord, and laſt of all the ſon himſelf, hath been ſent away without fruit, and evilly intreated, and violent hands laid on them and the heir not owned <hi>to be Lord of and e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:48198:7" rendition="simple:additions"/>
the inheritance,</hi> the provocation is aggravated and the mans condemnation the more juſt, in the wilful diſpite of and againſt the ſpirit of grace, and for his own name ſake is he thus ariſen, that he may get himſelf a name and a praiſe (in the ſalvation or deſtruction of ſuch he comes to plead with <hi>(in mercy and the free grace of his love,)</hi> wherein he begins as an enemy and as ſubmiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on is found and witneſſed <hi>(under Judgement)</hi> friendſhip and unity is witneſſed, and the breach made up and all ſtill and quiet. Yea and was it not a favour <hi>in God</hi> to bear with this tree beyond the time of his firſt gathering <hi>(the time that Judgement was due to it, and that God came forth in the Judgement of and againſt his creature, in a ſtate he is fallen in and under?)</hi> that paſſing by he ſhould find it cumbring the ground, and have no fruit to his praiſe or any thing from thence brought forth pleaſant to his taſte and is it not the favour, grace, and mercy of God, is the ground of thy being, and if it be not of thy well being; is it not becauſe of thy ſin and offence againſt it? for there was goodneſs <hi>in God</hi> in his forbearance, and bearing with thee <hi>to this day,</hi> but if he can have no more good from and in thee <hi>thereby,</hi> ſay not he hath dealt hardly <hi>in this kinde;</hi> for on Gods part there is goodneſs in the ground of thy being <hi>(which honoreth his forbearance)</hi> and if it be not anſwered <hi>on thy part;</hi> this is the continual voice and cry of God <hi>in that ſoul</hi> that which is good is cumbered, the feild is over grown with weeds <hi>(netles and bryars and thorns,</hi> and theſe choak the good ſeed:) but when the ground is ſeen bad; <hi>either high<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way ground, or ſtony; or thorny</hi> its nigh unto curſing, whoſe end is to be burnt; and this is a very ſad ſtate, <hi>where mercy and favour hath left</hi> man to the ſecond death <hi>of Judgements decreeing,</hi> and that beares with the man, waiting to honor and get God a name in its execution; therefore ought the furrow ground to be ploughed up and no more to ſowe among thornes.</p>
               <p>So this tree is that the man that hath been ſown to <hi>(that which is of the fleſh being fleſh, as that which is of the ſpirit is ſpirit;)</hi> which man lives in and reaps and injoyes that <hi>which he hath been ſown to and in,</hi> and if it be of the fleſh, of the fleſh it reapes corruption; for the works of each body and ſpirit is ripe <hi>for tryal</hi>
                  <pb n="12" facs="tcp:48198:8" rendition="simple:additions"/>
and to receive Judgement is ready, which muſt be born by, and reſt &amp; end on the <hi>tranſgreſſor;</hi> (though it hath begun or may begin on the creature of God;) And though the works of many doth ſuffer loſs <hi>in this particular,</hi> yet ſo as their perſons ſhall be ſaved alive, <hi>in this day of the Lord Ieſus;</hi> but where Judgement goes a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the body, <hi>the tree or man;</hi> if the creature be not dead to it, and it to him, how hard is it to be born? And the more juſt judgement is, the more painful is it <hi>to be born by a life in the creature.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>So this is the ſume of what hath been ſayed, what fruit was brought forth to God (before his truth was profeſſed) was in a green tree and then was the wild olive ſtanding, and the wild vine and grapes was brought forth, and as their Judgement was without and in the firſt man, they have found hard meaſure, and were beaten with a few ſtripes (that which was under the Law and had its meaſure from men with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out mercy,) in a time of profeſſion, there Judgement is only with the Lord, and their fruit called for &amp;c. (Though ſuch hath been and are beaten with a few ſtripes, and hath the like meaſure meated from God, as they have meaſured to him <hi>[in his requirings of their duty to his creature,]</hi> and do taſte of the bitter things of his houſe, as he hath taſted of their bitter fruit,) as the fruitleſs and barren tree, that hath worren out the patience and forbearance of God, and hath drawn forth the ſtrength of the root into a bare and meer ſhow and profeſſion, flouriſhing with leaves only, but hath no fruit <hi>of that which it makes a ſhew of and profeſſeth in the world;</hi> This is it that hath a curſe at its root; which the Axe of God is layed to, whereas under the law, when the fruit was only ſower and unpleaſant, bitter to the taſte of God, and unſavoury in the noſtriles of the holy one <hi>(when as in a ſenſure, it was offered to him as inſence,)</hi> the axe was onely layed to the branches, to the bodyes ſpreading forth; but now cut it down <hi>ſaith the Lord,</hi> why cumbers it the ground? Oh that this could be read! for great is the work of God, in reveal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the miſtery hereof <hi>in this day;</hi>
               </p>
               <p>For it is this tree God is diſpleaſed with <hi>(in the biterneſs of his ſoul)</hi> that hath not the nature and virtue and ſap of the life it
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:48198:8" rendition="simple:additions"/>
makes ſhew of and profeſſeth <hi>(to and in the worlds eye and ſight,)</hi> whereby the name of God is blaſphemed and ſpoken evil of <hi>by and through them;</hi> that have been branching forth themſelves into ſeveral Judgements and perſwaſions of opinion, and the ſtrength of all they labour and indeavour after <hi>is</hi> but to make a fair ſhew in the fleſh, and to inſult over ſuch they have power over <hi>in this par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticular<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
                  </hi> and ſo is fit for nought, but the fire: for the ſower grapes though they were unpleaſant to Gods taſte <hi>(ſu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>h that our fathers or father eat of this tree)</hi> and the childrens teeth hath thereby been ſet an edge, whereby the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>nger of what was raiſed and kindled, hath diſcovered Gods countenance <hi>(not to be his wounted favour &amp; way and courſe of doing good)</hi> whereby the ſons of men have ſeen themſelves threatned, with the diſpleaſure of God, <hi>that which was thus unpleaſant to his reliſh;</hi> yet ſhall this proverb no more be uſed in our Land <hi>(the fathers have eaten ſower grapes and the childrens teeth are ſet on edge )</hi> but as what was done in a green tree hath been favourably dealt with, and the branches thereof <hi>only</hi> cropt, and taken away, as a time of ignorance God winked at much of theſe things, and chaſtiſed them with rods <hi>only</hi> but now with Scorpions; then with a few ſtripes, but now with many (and concerning this <hi>ſaith my ſoul,</hi> oh that the ſtates hereof could be diſtinguiſhed of <hi>in the world</hi>)</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>
                  <hi>Concerning the words of Chriſt,</hi> fear not him that can kill the body; but fear ye him that is able to deſtroy both body and ſoul, and caſt it into hell fire:</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>Intorduct,</hi> Becauſe the Judgement of God is eternal, and the fire is everlaſting <hi>into whoſe burning flames the wicked is and are to be caſt,</hi> it hath become a common proverb <hi>in the world,</hi> that out of hell is no redemption; though there may be and are many <hi>already</hi> in it that thus are uſeing and exclaiming this meſſage <hi>unto others:</hi> and that both ſuch and all others may have a care <hi>for the future,</hi> what they ſay and pronounce <hi>in ſuch caſes;</hi> I proceed to declare:</p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="14" facs="tcp:48198:9" rendition="simple:additions"/>Firſt, What hell is? And who thoſe are that already are in it?</p>
               <p>Hell is utter darkneſs, and its fire is the unquenchable fury of the wrath of Gods judgement, <hi>in the torment of the wicked:</hi> but though it be ſo to a nature and ſtate the creature <hi>mankind,</hi> was once fallen into and under, yet it is not abſolutely ſo to the crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture of God, <hi>in any ſtate he hath been betrayed into, and hath ſo fallen in and under:</hi> for there is a great deal of difference between the man of ſin and worker of inequity (the enemy of mankind <hi>un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der whoſe power the creature of God hath fallen,</hi>) and the creature it ſelf thus betrayed <hi>(by the ſubtle alurements and temptation of the ſerpent, and Satan, that old deceiver of mankind;)</hi> Yea and the creature of God ſhall be redeemed and reſtored <hi>in all the world,</hi> into that ſtate <hi>of liberty,</hi> and under that <hi>ſubjection</hi> God firſt placed and ſtated him in, and though God created all things for himſelf, and the wicked for the day of deſtruction: yet did not God create them wicked, but that ſtate they were lead into, <hi>under the power of the deſtroyer,</hi> that thereby hath deceived the creature of that peace and comfort <hi>in the world, that ſtands in time and place,</hi> that otherwayes was <hi>therein</hi> peculiar to him, and that he might have injoyed (whoſe ſuch day of deſtruction he <hi>the deſtroyer</hi> called to himſelf,) though the day God created: even this day that ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifeſteth the deſtroyer and power of deſtruction, that God in eternity and his equal decreeings <hi>(that meaſures to every one and thing a juſt recompence of reward)</hi> had ordained and meaſureth back to him, and on his own head, what he thus awakened to the creature <hi>(that is now returned to and on himſelf;)</hi> There<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore,</p>
               <p>Such are already in hell,</p>
               <p>Who are not or hath not been brought down into a ſence and filling of the creatures miſery <hi>(under the power of the deſtroyer and devourer;)</hi> for thither was Chriſt Jeſus (the lambe of God that taketh away the ſin of the world, that was made ſin for us, though he knew no ſin <hi>in himſelf,</hi> but took on him the infirmities of na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, <hi>ſin was the cauſe of,</hi> and ſuffered the curſe of the Law <hi>due to ſin,</hi> and that was added becauſe of ſin and tranſgreſſion <hi>againſt
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:48198:9" rendition="simple:additions"/>
God</hi>) brought, and he indured the ſhameful curſed death of the Croſs, to teach and lead the creature <hi>of God</hi> what he was to wait in, to feel the power of, <hi>to the overcoming the curſe;</hi> for it was writ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten <hi>in the Law</hi> curſed was every one that hanged on a tree; and this curſe came on the tranſgreſſor <hi>first</hi> and was added becauſe of tranſgreſſion, and a ſence and feeling of this condition are all to come into <hi>for the creatures ſake,</hi> ere the tranſgreſſion can be re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moved, and he that is really the tranſgreſsor brought to judge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment and condigne puniſhment; for though the woman <hi>the crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture of God,</hi> was firſt found in tranſgreſſion <hi>(that was created for the man,)</hi> and the man <hi>in this ſtate</hi> is by the woman, yet the man of ſin, <hi>that man by whom ſin came,</hi> was the cauſe of and in the ground of her betraying <hi>(who was created to be the mans glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry [in this fallen ſtate] as he was created to be the glory or Image of God.)</hi> And it is he that was in the cauſe <hi>of</hi> and rejoyceth <hi>in</hi> the creatures fall and deſtruction <hi>(that was not nor is not Gods creature)</hi> that God will deſtroy by his coming, <hi>in the brightneſs of his appearance, and by the breath of his mouth and nostriles:</hi> And</p>
               <p>Thus are all to conſider, the man is but one <hi>[that hath ſoul and body]</hi> and the way <hi>of God is</hi> but one, and the fire of Gods eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal Judgement <hi>(that is fury and wrath to the wicked)</hi> is but one; and this fire is the curſe &amp; pain of death <hi>(the torment thereof is,)</hi> that which the enemy kindled and awakened under the ſufferance of God <hi>(wherein God is called and termed a conſuming fire;)</hi> Yea and this fire is to be indured <hi>[by all,]</hi> that he may be known that can indure everlaſting burnings, and can dwell with and in con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſuming fire <hi>(where God is come to ſit [in his people] as a refiner;)</hi> But though the creature was once found in tranſgreſſion <hi>the firſt man Adam was;</hi> And though the curſe of the Law <hi>of men</hi> reſted and reſteth on the juſt and innocent, yet the judgement of God hath begun at the houſe of God <hi>(where the Judgement of men and curſe of their Law hath reſted;)</hi> And into this ſence and feeling, even of ſufferance with the juſt, and to the bearing the waite and burthen of and on the creature and creation <hi>of God,</hi> are all to come; for <hi>there</hi> is Chriſt Jeſus <hi>the juſt,</hi> this ſuffering ſeed and ſpirit of God; and whoever feeleth or hath a ſence <hi>of
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:48198:10" rendition="simple:additions"/>
him,</hi> hath that ſence firſt raiſed <hi>of him</hi> in a ſuffering condition, and comes to ſuffer <hi>with him;</hi> as did <hi>David, that came the right way to God,</hi> and felt him <hi>in the ſeed and ſpirit of life</hi> in a ſuffering condition, and for that cauſe was his ſoul in hell or grave (under the power of the enemies work, firſt awakened temptation to that, which being overcome by <hi>[as Gods witneſs was and is awakened in the ſoul]</hi> the torment of fear and terror <hi>[of and in death,]</hi> made him cry out under, <hi>my ſins are a burden to heavy for me to bear;)</hi> and whether ſhall I ſly <hi>from thy preſence,</hi> If I go into hell <hi>thou art there,</hi> and in the bottom of the Sea <hi>alſo,</hi> for mighty waves had went <hi>over his ſoul,</hi> and he ſaw the grave of the wicked, and the place of the ungodly (where they dwell <hi>that are ſet in ſlipery places;</hi>) but he was aſſured, that God would not leave his ſoul there <hi>(in hell or the grave,)</hi> nor ſuffer his holy one to ſee corrup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion; for the Lord ſayed unto my Lord <hi>ſayed he,</hi> ſit thou at my right hand, untill I make thy foes my footſtool; ſo</p>
               <p>The dwelling and keeping in a ſence and feeling of that ſtate and condition the creature or creation of God is <hi>in all the world,</hi> is to be in the way and hope of the redemption of God, and to have the faith of God <hi>[in his ſon]</hi> concerning the work of reſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration; for it is the miſery and ſad ſtate <hi>of the world,</hi> that they are unſenceable of their miſery, and the ſadneſs of that ſtate <hi>they are in and under;</hi> and therefore is it the houſe of darkneſs, and utter darkneſs will be their portion; if they come not this way, even to that which awakeneth the ſence of ſin, and of the creatures mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſery <hi>therein and under;</hi> for in that ſtate of darkneſs and blindneſs of mind, eternity and endleſs ſeperation ſteals on the creature, and he ſlips into the pit and ditch <hi>out of which is no recovery;</hi> And this is to have ſoul and body caſt into hell fire, when in the body of nature a fire is kindled, and wrath come forth, in refer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ance to the power of the enemy and deſtruction <hi>the creature in that state hath favoured,</hi> and wherein the humors of the mind hath lodged, that leads into and creates humors of body <hi>favour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able</hi> to deaths power and dominion<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> yet I would not have it concluded that the juſt ſeed of God and ſpirit of life <hi>in the crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture and creation,</hi> or the creature it ſelf, is alwayes to continue in
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:48198:10" rendition="simple:additions"/>
and under ſuſferance in the world, though wh<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>le the world is in this ſtate and condition <hi>things now ſtanding in and under,</hi> needs muſt the ſufferance thereof continue; And the creature is not to go out of the ſence and feeling of the ſtate and condition the Juſtice is in, <hi>in the general,</hi> into hardneſs of Judgement againſt the creature of God <hi>in the world,</hi> becauſe of any experience of deliverance <hi>in the particular,</hi> out of ſuch ſtate the generality of people layes in and under, and ſo in that hard mind and ſtate, to cloſe up themſelves againſt mercy, and pitty, and limit God to the will of any creaturely Judgement; for the ſufferance of and in the body of nature <hi>(in the ſtate things now ſtand in and under)</hi> cannot for ever continue <hi>to and in the creature of God,</hi> but drives it to its eternal home <hi>(which rules in and over the world, and is God in the ſpirit of the world)</hi> to the ſetting the creature of God at li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berty <hi>(that hath been in bondaged under the power hereof.)</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>The Difference between the creatures Sinning againſt the Judgement of God <hi>[in a time of ignorance, before God was known and acquainted with,]</hi> and againſt his mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy and grace, after he hath made known and revealed himſelf in his preſence <hi>(of joy, favour, and loving kindneſs.)</hi>
               </head>
               <p>Which is <hi>A precious warning and viſitation</hi> (of repentance) <hi>to all the world; but eſpecially to thee</hi> (O England!)</p>
               <p>Oh World! World! and in thee (O <hi>England!</hi>) this is not ſo much a threatning thee with what is to come to paſs as a warning and viſitation <hi>(of information)</hi> for the turning your minds to the
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:48198:11" rendition="simple:additions"/>
light of Chriſt and ſpirit of God <hi>(in your hearts,)</hi> that you may ſee <hi>(from the King on the throne, to the maid that grindes on the mill or bagger on the dunghil,)</hi> that God is no reſpector of perſons but is this day come down into the earth to viſit for the ſins of all <hi>(high and low rich and poor and none ſhall go free and e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcape the hand of his Judgement herein,)</hi> for your ſins are ripe and ready for deſtruction.</p>
               <p>And this day is your ſin and offence againſt the ſpirit of God <hi>(or God who is a Spirit)</hi> aggravated againſt him; in that it is now a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt his mercy &amp; the love of his pity &amp; free grace <hi>(ye are thus found ſinning and offending againſt him,)</hi> from the head to the foot, and ſo throughout the whole body of nature <hi>[in creation]</hi> wherein the favour and forgiveneſs of God hath been much wronged and a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>buſed <hi>(by their ſlighting the ſa<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                        <desc>•••</desc>
                     </gap>)</hi> which in dayes of old was only againſt the Judgement of God, and that in a time of Igno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance <hi>(Wherein the creature knew not God, nor his Judgements the ſin and offence was againſt,)</hi> which cauſed God the more to wink at their faults, and to correct them lightly <hi>[with rods,]</hi> for that they knew not him, nor the mind and will of his ſpirit <hi>[in judgement,]</hi> that the ſin and offence was thus to and againſt, though ſufferance and afflictions followed ſuch the creature <hi>[for his evil,]</hi> but it was good from God <hi>(thus to follow with judgement)</hi> that the creature might thereby come to ſee his ſin, and him that he thus had ſinned and offended againſt, and learn good under the ſame, to mourn for him he thus had ſinned and offended againſt <hi>[in a time of ignorance,]</hi> and this was a time of tryal <hi>[of his patience]</hi> though he ſuffered for evil doing, where ſtooping under the Judgement or Judgements of God, he there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by came to learn wiſdom of him to know his ſpirits coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſellings; even the counſellings of his law <hi>(which is light in the heart or conſcience;)</hi> for before I was aflicted <hi>(ſaid David)</hi> I went aſtray, but now I have learned thy Law, and thy Law is light &amp;c. And oh how I love thy Law <hi>(and the judgements and ſtatutes thereof; that are ſweeter to me then the hony and hony combe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>)</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="19" facs="tcp:48198:11" rendition="simple:additions"/>Thus was Judgement the creatures teacher and inſtructer <hi>(in a ſtate under the Law, whereby came up the prophecy or ſight of a bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter and more acceptable day and ſtate of the love of God)</hi> and this hath been loved, even the Judgements of God <hi>(to and on a ſtate as it was and is due to,)</hi> how hath the creature been kept low under judgement <hi>(in a ſtate of fear and trembling?)</hi> and the love of God <hi>hereby</hi> hath come to grow and increaſe <hi>in the heart;</hi> and ſo that which firſt appeared in the judgement turned into mercy and love, and is the free grace of God <hi>(to and in his creature)</hi> for the firſt diſcovery of God <hi>[is]</hi> in judgement <hi>(to a ſtate in the creature it is due to;)</hi> and as that is kept to <hi>at home, and the</hi> creaturely will and ſtrivings, and ſtruglings <hi>watched over,</hi> a ſhort work is made in the Earth <hi>(in what ſtoopes to judgement [in God] and to be counſelled by his ſpi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>,)</hi> and thats become the mercy love and free grace of God <hi>to ſuch his creature, i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> the loving re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiving thereof)</hi> that firſt appeared in judgement (in which an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger and fury and wrath began to be kindled <hi>to and in his creature,</hi> and accordingly is meaſured back <hi>(in what is broke forth in and on the world,)</hi> but if the creature go on in ſin and offence againſt this the judgement of G<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <hi>(though in the execution thereof ſuffer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ance hath purſued him therein,)</hi> and a ſtop was put to his way and courſe ſo that he could not any longer go on <hi>therein,</hi> but was forced to ſtoop thereto <hi>(becauſe his way was hedged up with thornes)</hi> yet as ſufferance <hi>[under Iudgement,]</hi> any white ſtayed and reſted, hath taken occaſion thereby to ſtrengthen himſelf in ſin and offence againſt the ſame <hi>(oh this is againſt the mercy, and favour, and love of God!)</hi> And it becomes much worſe, and the offence of greater (thus to ſin againſt the favour and grace of God <hi>[in love, mercy, pity and compaſſion to his creature)</hi> then the ſin and offence meerly againſt the Judgement of God (in the creatures ignorance, that knew not him <hi>(in the mind and will thereof,)</hi> that the ſin and offence was againſt;) which as it is thus aggravated <hi>by what hath abounded,</hi> ſtrengtheneth the Judgement of God againſt his creature (that was at firſt ordained againſt the ſin the creature was overcome and overpowered by <hi>(in which ſtate God reckoned him not for the ſinner)</hi> but chaſtiſed him
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:48198:12" rendition="simple:additions"/>
lightly and with a few ſtripes, to bring and lead him to the ſence he firſt departed from,) that now is chaſtiſed with ſcorpions and beaten with many ſtripes; Yea my heart bleeds in the conſidera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of thy offence <hi>(oh England!)</hi> in this particular, and let it be read both by King and People, Rulers, and Subjects <hi>(in that I am in good earneſt with ye all)</hi> that no longer ſhall your tryals be played and ſported with; for God will not be mocked <hi>(any longer by ye.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Oh Conſider, conſider! your ſin againſt his mercy, and fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vour, and gentle dealings, is a great aggravation of your offence, and makes it intolerable: What ſhall I ſay to ye? Or what ſhall I do for ye <hi>(that weary out the patience and long ſuffer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ance of God?)</hi> I have taken up a complaint, I mourn bit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terly and ſorely what grief is like my grief <hi>herein?</hi> will ye provoke God <hi>(as a man provoketh his enemy and adverſary,)</hi> and is it poſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble he ſhould always bear? O weep, repent and howle <hi>bitterly</hi> ye adulterors and adultereſſes <hi>(that have back-ſlided from God, and his Iudgements, Lawes and ſtatutes;)</hi> for ye all are gone a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtray, and are an adulterous generation; will ye always offend his patience <hi>(as a wicked man that tryes and ſtraines the patience of his friend;)</hi> and is it poſſible God ſhould always bear with ye? will ye ſtrive to ſtrain the Patience of God beyond its bent <hi>(becauſe he hath been long ſuffering and forbearing;)</hi> and think ye he will not be too ſtrong for ye?</p>
               <p>For as a man ſhould not ſtreign the curteſie of his friend <hi>(to the end of forbearance; or beyond the freedom thereof)</hi> to make him his enemy; and as he ſhould not provoke and ſtir up evil toward himſelf, and cauſe his own hurt and deſtruction; ſo will not the Lord alwaies hold him guiltleſs <hi>(in the nature hereof;)</hi> oh, is not! and hath it not been <hi>(the love of God)</hi> in the time of thy ignorance and want of knowledge of him, to put a ſtop to thy waies and courſe <hi>(as a ſtop to the way and courſe of a menſtrous Woman, as a hedge to the path of a whore and adultreſs from her husband,)</hi> when the Prince of the power of darkneſs had blinded thy eye <hi>(the god of this World that rules in the children of diſobedience)</hi> and the blind were leading the blind <hi>(until both were ready to fall and tumble in
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:48198:12" rendition="simple:additions"/>
the ditch?</hi> was it not his large favour to thee his creature <hi>(while in a ſtate of enmity againſt his ſpirit, and under the power and lea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding and guideance of the enemies,)</hi> to let thee ſee thy ſtate? and hath not the grace and favour and love and mercy <hi>[of God]</hi> ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peared and brok forth <hi>in the World?</hi> and doth it not ſhine in his forbearance <hi>to and of his creature?</hi> Oh! lay down, lay down ſtoop and give place! cry in ſecret, for God hath overtook thee <hi>(oh perverſe people!)</hi> And his grace is become their teacher of all them <hi>(that live godly, righteouſly, and ſoberly in this preſent evil world,)</hi> that denying ungodlineſs and worldly luſt, they ſhould ſo live and behave themſelves, as anſwer his witneſs in all hearts and not acquit God evil for his kindneſs, and provoke his jealouſy, which is over them for good,) againſt them for evil; but (as be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cometh Chriſtians) ſhould be armed with the ſame minde as was him they profeſs.</p>
               <p>Therefore let the minde and heart of all that God hath over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taken <hi>be awakened;</hi> ſee oh ſee againſt whom and what, ye have wounded, and pierced, and greeved, and return to him <hi>in that ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit</hi> that bears the weight and burthen of all on his ſhoulders: That ye may come to the repentance not to be repented of, <hi>in the godly ſorrow of heart,</hi> where ſin goes before hand to Judgement, and may no longer continue in the dayly and hourly repentings <hi>of the World,</hi> nor worldly ſorrow of men of corrupt mindes, that ſin wilfully after the knowledge of Gods truth hath been re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived <hi>in the heart,</hi> (and there hath been a taſting of the good gifts of God and the power of the world to come, and there remain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing nothing but a fearful looking for of Judgement;) for that day had not come if there had not been firſt a falling away, and departing from the truth; therefore muſt Judgement be ſtooped to and born and endured <hi>(on that minde and nature)</hi> in that the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pentings of the world <hi>(in the worldly minde and nature,)</hi> will not ſerve turn, will not renew to go they are ever to be repented of; and though it may not be wilfully and in diſpite to the ſpirit of grace <hi>(that all ſuch ſinnings are in and ſtands in the minde of,)</hi> yet they lead it to <hi>(in whom ever ſins after the knowledge of truth is recei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved</hi> where the ſin comes after to Judgement, and men dyeth in
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:48198:13" rendition="simple:additions"/>
their ſin, then whether he goeth <hi>[that forgiveth ſin]</hi> they cannot come; ſo to live in a ſtate where is the after Judgement, and after repentings <hi>(of the world,)</hi> is to live in a fearful troubled ſtate and condition there remaining nothing but a fearful looking for of Judgement, and fiery indignation from Heaven.</p>
               <p>Oh! I warn all people <hi>on the earth,</hi> never for time to come to charge any hardneſs on God, or that he is a hard maſter, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> But keep that on ſelf, that the creature of God may feel his love <hi>(whom his love is to)</hi> and may grow up in and under the ſame; for whatever is done from and in that hard and hardned ſpirit <hi>[a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the creature of God,] in the name of God,</hi> is thereby the more aggravated againſt God.</p>
            </div>
            <trailer>THE END.</trailer>
            <pb facs="tcp:48198:13"/>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
